[Music]
welcome to this business Central launch
event session on what's new in server
and database this is the third video
that we have and in the agenda of this
this is about web services
in this particular release wave we
didn't make it faster we didn't make new
features but we did actually make it a
lot more stable and and we hope that
that will make the life better for
customers and for you yes and the first
thing that we want to talk about is
probably also one of the ones that
you'll see the most which is an
improvement to our edit in Excel story
when you publish your data now o data V
before Pages evaluate the editable
property just like the UI does before it
only supported Boolean variables so what
you would see sometimes for instance in
the ship to code on the sales orders
page which has an editable property
which is calculated and not just a
simple um Boolean then when you were
publishing your data you would get an
error message about the property
editable and not being valid Etc meaning
that a number of pages couldn't be used
for edit in Excel and remember in
general you should use API pages instead
of normal Pages exposed to O data but
for editing Excel we want that to mimic
the UI Behavior which is why behind the
scenes that uses o data on top of UI
pages so it's mainly for that
functionality that this is
relevant other service
calls um have also received some
stability improvements we have made sure
that the server now returns return code
503 if your request waits in the request
queue and you end up timing out and you
will get a retry after header back and
you can then decide to retry the call
later this has been backported and is
available from 22.2 and this is one of
the examp there will be many of these
examples you need to up your game on the
clients on the web service clients you
write the code you write because we are
now offering you and also expecting you
toh deal with return codes to look for
headers and make your clients much more
stable so together with the server is
giving you that information and your
clients reacting on it your client code
can simply be much much more resilient
to to failures or transient
things
yes now another place where we've added
more stability is when we have invalid
metadata which for instance can be that
you have duplicates in the uh metadata
so you end up with two pages named the
same stuff that can happen when you have
multiple extensions in install and
before it would be very obvious at least
for the customer that something was
wrong because all web services would
fail and now the one that causes the
failure is ignored and we emit partner
Telemetry so you shouldn't rely on your
customer calling you anymore you should
rely on Telemetry instead and I think
that's a much better story if you look
in the Telemetry app you'll see that
there is a new page where you can find
the web service end points that fail at
runtime and it also hints at how you can
actually fix them and if if you really
want to take it to the next level you
you just don't just have a powerbi app
but you actually alert reactively on
these failures so that you know before
the customer knows or yes and that would
be even better that is of course the
professional way of making use of
telemetry
right in Microsoft we abev at everything
so we don't call it a troubleshooting
guide we call it a tsg because it's much
faster to say tsg and we even have a
threel acronym for thre L acronym which
is T that is correct now to make it
easier for you to troubleshoot web
services we added a number of tsds this
is the first one um this helps you to
look at HP status codes what what they
mean and and what to do about them so
this first tsg is about okay if I get a
400 depending on whether it is incoming
or outbound web services how can I fix
that so go use stocks much more and that
will actually help you hopefully
troubleshoot web service calls
specifically for this we added a number
of things in the in the powerbi apps the
first is if you start putting user agent
in your web service calls that actually
survives all the way in Telemetry or
into the server and Emitt it to
Telemetry so the the first box here on
uh on the right um shows you which web
service clients are having problems
right so if you use a user agent you can
see it in the app and you can see oh
it's this particular web service client
that has the problem we also add
exceptions and Al call Stacks so you can
also see that together with the user
agent
the next thing is um return status codes
or return codes HTTP so the apps both
for incoming and outgoing web service
calls now have better visuals on HP
status and also better filters so you
can filter on on a given status code
look up in the TSD about what is this
and then start improving that part of
your
code same goes for outgoing out going
web services you also get this new uh
filtering and status code
visuals and then in the last release we
added or actually some releases ago we
added a queue for web service ingoing
web service calls because if you are
flooding uh the server with a lot of
calls we we we want to make sure that
server survives and we just can handle
things as we have available resources
become uh available these this queuing
time is now also showing up in Telemetry
so you can see Q time statistics both in
Telemetry and in the power Pi
reports the most effective way to not
have issues with web services is to co
is to write robust code so what uh we
apart from tsgs we also added uh error
handling best practices when you use
http client out to call out to external
services and we made actually a huge
makeover of the doc documentation for HP
client I'll just go through a few of
these examples first of all an endtoend
article on how to use uh HP client how
to set up run and and check for
things uh we also explain how HP client
send calls can fail so the different
ways they can do that as as well as
proper copy to clipboard code on error
handling for um uh the first part of
setting up as well as when you pass the
results um when you pass the result from
the service you also need to check for
status codes and there's also code that
you can just copy and make your code
resilient especially for HSP status it
could be some of these um are just that
external service saying hey wait a
minute you need to back up a bit so you
can also put uh in code here for retry
strategies and then make your code more
resilient in in case the the service
you're calling is having some transient
issues and then we explain as I
mentioned um all the common HP error
codes uh with also suggested Solutions
whether you have inbound calls or
outbound
calls we also made it possible um when
you call uh when you call out in case
web web HP client send fails even before
passing return code there are different
ways it can do it maybe you you didn't
write the correct URL or maybe you have
a network error or maybe you have a
certificate error so we made that easier
for you to troubleshoot if you use get
last error text you can now simply copy
that into your um into the error message
next slide here um so that if if
customers are calling you with some
problem if they copy that in you can
actually get the error message and you
can troubleshoot from there some
examples here before if you had SSL
connection failures um the error message
would prior to to where version 23 would
just be see inner exceptions but you had
no idea about what the inner exception
was so that that's kind of ha see it but
we won't show you now we actually showed
or at least give you a little bit more
info in this case the remote certificate
is invalid okay that's much easier to
troubleshoot if you actually know that
another example here is um also for for
a certificate whereas before you would
just get something but in fact the
problem uh that was from the inner
exception was padding is invalid and
cannot be removed and and you need to
fix your code so it's just giving you
some better options to find out what's
what's
wrong and a small thing behind the
scenes is that we've optimized our usage
of sockets because before actually a
large number of outgoing calls using the
HTTP client could potentially start the
VM for ports um so we're making more
reuse Etc and we've backported that and
that is the way we've been running even
back to version
2.x and it's not something that you
really need to do any changes about it's
just for your information in case youve
seen some of these
issues there are also a few upcoming
changes the schema version for custom
apis will change its default and we are
removing the support for Delta links
it's already not really supported there
are very very few users of this
functionality and we will be removing
that so
Goos go check if you have metadata
issues use to limitu to find it and fix
it yeah and also make sure that you
harden your code for interacting with
web services both the incoming request
where you should handle the Response
Code correctly
decide on a back off strategy Etc and
look at the troubleshooting guide and
Harden it and same thing for the
outgoing calls you can hand the erors an
Al code and you can provide relevant
details in as detailed information and
of course also there consider retrying
and then stop using Delta links the
feature is deprecated as Yen showed in
the last slide it's going to be removed
in 2024 Wave 1 so you have six months to
uh to stop using it and then we'll
remove it from the
service other sessions that could be
relevant if you like this is uh the
compiler and developer tools session
what's new in developer tools and a new
kit on the Block yeah the what's new in
database data verse and dynamic 365 app
integration part two will cover business
events uh which is also tightly related
to webs
services and then my good friend Kenny
yeah as an we also always have the watch
new and Telemetry session um bits and
bites small nuggets of things you can
use to make your life easier using
Telemetry yeah and of course we refer to
the normal resources Yammer x bc BC
ideas and join office hours if you can
and with that thank you very much for
watching thanks for having
us